DAVID FATSEAS



FATSEASD@GMAIL.COM



+61 488 07 6006



DAVID FATSEAS @ LINKEDIN

SUMMARY OF EXPERIENCE

Over 30 years of experience in the telecommunications industry, taking on both pioneering and leadership roles in the design, testing and deployment of 1st to 5th Generation Mobile Networks throughout Europe, Middle-East and Asia-Pacific.

Worked in both Public Sector and Private Sector Organizations, including: Queensland Railways, Queensland Public Works Department, Ericsson, Nokia, Nortel Networks, KPN Orange, Saudi Telecom, Vodafone, O2, Telstra & NBN.

LEADERSHIP SKILLS

A proven record of success as a technology introduction and deployment strategist, solution development innovator and leader of a specialist network engineering teams.

Possess exceptional inter-personal communication and able to simply and clearly articulate complex subject matters to all levels of an organization.

EDUCATION

- Bachelor of Engineering Electronics & Communications (Queensland Institute of Technology - 1986)
- Master of Engineering and Technology Management (University of Queensland 1995)
- Master of Computing (University of Southern Queensland - 2014).

RECENT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SOLUTIONS ARCHITECT - WIRELESS / NBN CO

2021 to Present Day

Recently joined the NBN where I am leading the introduction of new router platform throughout the fixed wireless network (~2,400 Sites). The solution will lay the foundation for the introduction of the next generation (5G) RAN technologies and evolution of the transport network (namely: Migration from Layer 2 to Layer 3 Backhaul, Software Defined Networking, Bandwidth Optimizing Networking, and other Network Automation capability).

SENIOR LEAD/TECHNOLOGY TEAM MANAGER / TELSTRA

2014 to 2021

Leading for a small team of specialist network engineers, responsible for the development, verification and delivery of end-to-end network solutions and associated platforms/features forming part of Telstra's legacy 3G & 4G and future 5G Mobile Network. Key achievements in the role include: (1) Driving the transitions from TDM to Ethernet, and Ethernet to IP Backhaul as part of the evolution of the Telstra Mobile Network, (2) Facilitating the evolution of RAN from the legacy Distributed (D-RAN) Architecture to a Centralized (C-RAN) Architecture to enable enhanced network perform capabilities, (3) Introducing virtualized network functions for the 1st time into the Mobile Network (ie: virtualized security gateway, virtualized traffic measurement & monitoring application, and virtualized radio access functions used to automate network integration) and (4) World 1st Introduction of Packetized Fronthaul for 5G Network. More recently tasked with the identifying key enablers and developing strategies for fully programmable and flexible 5G RAN Transport Network. My contributions to the overall end-to-end Optical and IP Network Strategy are helping to drive network performance enhancements, providing greater network resilience, assuring the security of network infrastructure and integrity of user/management traffic, and identifying opportunities to reduce capital and operational expenditure through innovation, simplification and automation.

MEMBERSHIPS, TRAINING & SPECIALIST SKILLS

Preparation training for CompTIA Security+ (SY0-601) Certification Completed, Exam to be scheduled.

Software Defined Networking (SDN) & Network Function Virtualization (NFV) Certification Completed - Box Hill Institute, Victoria (2017).

Micro-Credential in Software Defined Networking (SDN) completed – RMIT (2021).

Private Edge & Centralized Cloud (NFVi, NaaS, IaaS) based Radio Access Network Architecture Training completed.

Subject Matter Expert in 4G & 5G Transport Network Architecture (D-RAN, C-RAN, E-RAN & V-RAN), Network Automation & Network Virtualization Infrastructure (NFVi).

Subject Matter Expert in Terrestrial Optical Fiber, Microwave Fronthaul /Backhaul & Satellite Backhaul Systems.

Extensive knowledge of Cisco, Juniper, Ericsson, Nokia, ZTE and Huawei based Network Switching & Routing (Edge/Access) Platforms, Features and Functions.

Extensive knowledge of Network Element, Network Management & Network Orchestration Systems.

Trained in Project Management, including AGILE methods of project delivery (including use of JIRA and CONFLUENCE Tools/Systems).

Experienced in CI/CD and DevOPS styles of solution delivery practices.

Experienced in both Project & Contract Management (Building Construction), acting as the Superintendent's Representative under Contract.

Registered Professional Engineer in Queensland (RPEQ # 04151).

RECENT PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (CONT.)

SENIOR TECHNOLOGY SPECIALIST / TELSTRA

2008 to 2014

Leading the development and deployment of network solutions to allow Mobiles Traffic to agreed system performance and cost objectives.

Technologies, Systems and Methodologies used to achieved network performance objectives include Ultra-Low Latency/Ultra-Low Jitter Switching & Routing Networking, Optical Transport Networking, DWDM, Satellite Backhaul, CPRI & eCPRI Fronthaul Systems, SD-WAN, Network Virtualization & Cloud Based Architecture, High Accuracy Network Synchronisation (NTP, PTP, GPS, SyncE), IP Security Enablement, Network Analytics and Performance Management, Network Configuration Data Standardization, and Quality of Service Policies.

TELECOM CONSULTANT / O2-TELEFONICA GERMANY

2006 to 2007

Specialist Consultant, responsible for the planning and delivery of ATM Transport Network Solutions across Germany and responsible for ATM Transport Network Planning Tool Development. At the time, this was the largest Alcatel-Lucent ATM PSAX based Network outside of USA (consisting of 1000+ Network Switching Elements, connecting ~10,000 2G Mobile Sites).

SOFTWARE PROGRAM MANAGER / NOKIA POLAND

2004 to 2005

In-charge of Nokia's Mobile Network Dimensioning & Planning Tool Roadmap & Feature Development. A key achievement during my time with Nokia was the leading centralization and hosting of Radio, Transmission and Core Network Planning Software and associated mapping databases to allow Nokia's Network Planning Teams securely access the software.

PRINCIPAL ENGINEER / AAPCS (KORDIA) AUSTRALIA

2004

Leading a small specialist team of the engineers as part of the planning, deployment and modernizing/capacity uplifting of transmission network for the Vodafone Network across Victoria.

TELECOM CONSULTANT / SAUDI TELECOM

2003

Responsible for the planning and deployment of Microwave Transmission Network Solutions for the Saudi Telecom 2G Network.

STATE TRANSMISSION MANAGER / HUTCHISON AUSTRALIA

2002

Leading a mid-sized (~30 engineers/integrators) Transmission Network Planning and Transmission Network Deployment Team, ensuring that network launch & network expansion readiness of the "3" Network in NSW.